I'm Dr. Joe Neely.
I practice with the Barton Oaks Dental Group.
We're going to talk about the symptoms of a toothache.
Obviously, the main symptom of the toothache, is pain.
The more specific, in terms of breaking down pain, would be whether the pain was sharp and intense, or dull and unrelenting.
Typically, the sharp intense pains come suddenly, and then are gone.
The deeper pains are probably not as sharp, or are sudden of impact, but they stay in just the simple length of time, is an issue.
Typically, if a tooth is sensitive to hot or cold, it means that the nerve in the tooth is still partially alive, and it can respond to temperature.
If the tooth is sensitive to air, that also is an indication, that the tooth is still alive.
Maybe damaged, may have some other issues, but there's still some live nerve tissue.
When a tooth is sensitive to pressure, then it typically will mean that you either have a fracture, something moving inside the tooth, or up against the gum, or an infection contained in the structure around the tooth, be it gum or bone, but it's trapped in between two structures, and the pressure from that infection, causes pain.